You know the carousels I've made using
Chat GPT image too and actually posted
one of them on my Instagram. It got
nearly 100,000 views and a lot of
engagement as you can see here. Each
carousel only took me like 15 minutes to
make which most of that time was spent
me waiting for Chat GPT to actually
generate different variations and the
system is actually very simple once you
understand how Chat GPT image model
actually works. By the end of this video
you'll have your own system to automate
your carousels as well. And to be honest
with you I'm pretty bad at design. I
used to spend hours on Canva trying to
find a template that would fit the vibe.
And once I find it, I'll spend way too
long tweaking it and making it perfect.
So the problem with most people when
they try using image gen like Chat GPT
or Nana Banana to generate carousels
that they would type something like
create me a six slide carousel about X.
And as a result they would get it back a
generic AI looking carousel and would
immediately give up. Then they would
blame the model and go back to Canva.
But the truth is is that image gen
models are only good at generating one
image at a time. The second you ask for
a full six slide carousel the whole
thing falls apart because each image is
not aware of each other. So essentially
creates a new image from the brief each
time. So the solution is to provide a
visual anchor for each slide generated.
The anchor is just your first slide done
very well. Once you have one slide that
nails the typography, the colors, the
mood, you attach it to every other slide
as a reference image. And now every new
slide generated is forced to match it.
Here are two carousels that were
generated giving the same topic and
brief. One is generating using one shot
prompt and another one was using slide
by slide generation. As you can see one
shot prompt carousel looks okay. It's a
bit messy. It just doesn't have any
taste. On the other hand, slide by slide
generated carousel looks very polished.
It's consistent from slide to slide.
Looks something like a designer would
make and think through. That's why a
carousel like this was able to generate
nearly 100,000 views. Every carousel has
to start with defining how many slides
there will be and what text should go on
each slide. This is probably the most
important step the majority people tend
to skip, but please don't skip it
because of copy as it doesn't
matter how pretty your carousel is. For
that reason, I created a project inside
ChatGPT called Instagram carousel copy
writer and I gave it two files that
tells ChatGPT how to write copy. Those
two files were trained on this
comprehensive document breaking down the
patterns of what makes carousel go
viral. And don't worry, all the
instructions and files will be in the
description. Now, we're just going to
give this project an idea and it'll give
us a copy for each slide. So, I already
prepared one already. I said, "Make me a
carousel about my morning routine and
habit." Which is actually all true. I
wake up every day at 7:00 a.m. I have a
cold shower. I do a bit of stretching. I
walk outside for 10 minutes to get
sunlight in my eyes. I journal and pray
for 10 minutes. I don't use my phone in
the first hour of the morning because it
disrupts the dopamine. All these habits
are actually true. I try to stretch
every day, but it doesn't really work.
And it gave me eight-slide carousel with
multiple hooks as an option.
Also gave me a caption and a hashtag.
You can go back and forth with it to
refine it further, but I'm pretty happy
with it. So, we can move on to the next
step. Now, we're going to find a visual
reference on how we want our Instagram
carousel to look like. For me, I want to
stand out with my carousels. So, I don't
actually look for inspiration on
Instagram. I prefer to look at
Pinterest. The reference could be
literally anything like a book cover or
a poster.
In my case, I found this and I think
it'll work perfectly. I'll be using this
image as a reference for my morning
routine Instagram carousel. Now, inside
my ChatGPT, I'm going to paste my visual
reference along with side with this
prompt. In this prompt, we're
essentially asking to create five
visually different versions for our hook
slide and we're telling it to use
reference image as a visual inspiration
only. Now, in the text for slide one
section, we're going to go back into our
chat and copy the slide one text. I'm
going to paste it in.
You can also play around with visual
directions if you want to include any
illustrations or brand guidelines if you
have any. From here, it will generate us
five different versions of the hook we
can pick from. And if you don't like any
of the versions, just keep asking until
you settle on something you're happy
with because this is the most important
step. This is your visual anchor and it
will set the mood for the rest of the
carousel. So, you should spend the most
time here to refine it until you're
happy with it. Now that we have our
visual anchor, in this case, I picked
this one. I like it the most. We're
going to generate the rest of the
slides. I'm using this prompt where I
will swap out all the text in square
brackets, the proper stuff that we got
from our copywriter project. For
example, this is
slide two text. I'm just going to copy
in here.
And adjust all the slide goals, slide
type, that all of that information is
given to you in this copy project. So, I
just paste it here in my visual anchor,
I pasted the prompt, and it gave us
three versions for each slide. The
reason why I like using multiple
versions is that it saves me a lot of
time from getting unexpected outputs.
For example, some of these don't quite
look right, but one of them actually
looks decent, so I'll pick this one and
I'll continue doing so. So, after around
10 minutes of prompting, giving a visual
anchors, we have eight slide carousel. I
downloaded them all into a folder and I
found this tool online just to show you
how this carousel would look like on
Instagram. Scrolling through, I can see
that this carousel has consistent font
and design system. It uses same colors
and elements and the positioning is
consistent from slide to slide. I'll be
happy to post that on my Instagram. And
sometimes you'll find that ChatGPT gets
you 90 or 95% there. The overall vibe is
right, but maybe one element or text is
slightly off. Instead of regenerating
the whole slide, I'll drop it into Canva
and use their magic layers. So, to use
that, go into Canva, go into homepage,
and you'll see magic layers. Click on
that and upload one of the slides you
generated. I already uploaded one, which
I hook slide.
And if I open the project, you'll see
that every layer is now editable. So,
the magic layers turns any image into
editable layers that you can move
around. So, I can move this
little thing around, and I can also
change the text to my
morning
routine.
I can't spell.
Um and I only use magic layers if the
fix is very small. Otherwise, I'll let
ChatGPT do all the heavy lifting. And
another cool thing you can do with the
system, you can also generate LinkedIn
infographics that currently crashing on
LinkedIn. For example, this infographic
is recently posted, has 1,200 likes, 400
comments, and probably got a lot of
leads. So, I found two infographics that
I wanted to copy, this one and this one.
And I gave it a prompt and I just said
recreate this infographic, and it
created this beautiful-looking LinkedIn
post that I can probably get couple of
hundred likes and couple of leads. So,
you don't have to use the system for
Instagram carousels. You can also use it
for LinkedIn, X, and any other social
media platform. So, if I had to
summarize this video, the whole thing is
just four simple steps. Make sure the
copy is good, meaning they have number
of slides and text for each slide. You
should spend 40% of the time here.
Number two, generate hook slide because
this will serve as your visual anchor
and will set the mood for the rest of
your carousel. You should spend 50% of
the time here. Number three, build one
slide at a time using the visual anchor
from step two as a style reference. You
should spend only 10% of your time here.
And if you want to make small tweaks
like text or spacing, use Canva magic
layers. And all my prompts,
instructions, and references will be in
the link down below. And if you want to
go deeper on stuff like this, I also
have a school community where we do a
weekly call where you can ask me any
questions. Link is also down below.
Hopefully, this system will help you
generate more content and spend less
time doing so. Subscribe for more videos
like this. I post them every week.